Guide to the Washington State Good Roads Association records 1883-1984 1883-2005
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Washington State Good Roads Association records
1883-2005
XOE_CPNWS0074wagoodr
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA, 98225-9123 360 650 7747 cpnws@wwu.edu
3.0 linear feet
The collection includes the business records of the Washington State Good Roads Association.
Washington State Good Roads Association
Biographical/Historical note
The Washington State Good Roads Association (WSGRA) was established in 1899 by Sam Hill to encourage development of an adequate and practical statewide highway system in Washington State. Sam Hill cultivated the support of non-profit civic groups interested in road-building and affiliated operations. The primary goal of the WSGRA was to establish a highway system created by the state legislature and operated under state management. The membership of WSGRA consisted mainly of county chapters representing local civic groups such as Chambers of Commerce and Granges. These local groups lobbied not only through WSGRA for the state-wide road network, but also in their local districts for improved road conditions. WSGRA was led by a president and was supported by an executive committee, consisting of one representative from each district. Districts were based on geographical divisions within the state. The yearly conferences involved delegates from the local organizations state-wide.
The Washington State Good Roads Association Records document the activities of the Washington State Good Roads Association (WSGRA) along with the North End Improvement Council (NEIC). These records also have some material from the Kitsap County Good Roads Association and the North Olympic Chamber of Commerce. The dates of the collection span from 1910-2005 and comprise three linear feet (6 boxes). Records include early and subsequent by-laws of the WSGRA, articles of association, a history of the organization, materials from conventions attended and organized, minutes, agendas, rollcalls and other information of some of the executive and annual member meetings; membership lists and profiles; financial records reflecting collection of membership dues and convention planning and execution; correspondence regarding membership, legislative activity, lobbying efforts, and inter-organizational relations; activities information including newsletters, pamphlets, and lobbying; newspaper clippings referring to the organization or road building; and some undated photographs. The NEIC records include by-laws, meeting minutes and proceedings, bank statements and financial quarterly statements, and correspondence. There is also some correspondence from the Kitsap County Good Roads Association, some subject file records from the North Olympic Chamber of Commerce, and some pamphlets and statements from other Good Roads Associations across the country.
The Washington State Good Roads Association records are organized in accordance with the following series arrangement:
Series I: Washington State Good Roads Association (WSGRA), 1910-2005
Sub-series 2. Financial Records, 1966-2005
Sub-series 3. Correspondence, 1913-2005
Sub-series 4. Activities, 1920-2003
Sub-series 5. Clippings, 1917-2000
Sub-series 6. Photos, undated
Series II: North End Improvement Council (NEIC) & Other Organizations, 1926-1980
Sub-series 1. North End Improvement Council (NEIC), 1926-1960
Sub-series 2. Kitsap County Good Roads Association, 1954-1960
Sub-series 3. North Olympic Chamber of Commerce, 1956-1957
Sub-series 4. Other Good Roads Associations, 1979-1980
The collection is open to the public.
Donated by Robert Teshara.
Hill, Samuel,--1857-1931.
Kitsap County Good Roads Association.; North End Improvement Council.; North Olympic Chambers of Commerce.; Washington State Good Roads Association
Pacific Coast Highway--History--Sources.; United States Highway 99--History--Sources.; Washington (State)--Politics and government--History--Sources.
Boards of Trade--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Highway planning--Washington (State)--Citizen participation--History--Sources.; Highway planning--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Lobbying--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Roads--Washington (State)--Design and Construction--History--Sources.; Transportation--Washington (State)--History--Sources.
Bellingham; Transportation; Washington State
- Washington State Good Roads Association (WSGRA), 1910-1987; Series I
  - Administrative Records, 1910-2005; Subseries 1
    - Bylaws, 1959-1980 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Articles of Association, 1995, 1999 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - History, 1935-1987 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - A Brief History of WSGRA... Samuel Hill, 1939 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Conventions
      - Speeches, Reports, 1948-1980 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Pamphlet Programs, 1938-1984 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Yakima, 1967 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Vancouver, 1980 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Ellensburg, 1981 (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Bellevue, 1982 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Olympia, 1983 (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Tacoma, 1990 (Box-folder 1/12)
      - Pasco, 2000 (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Tacoma, 2001 (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Spokane, 2003 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Proceedings, 1910-1935 (incomplete) (Box-folder 1/16)
      - Proceedings, 1936-1948 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Proceedings, 1949-1957 (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Proceedings, 1958-1970 (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Proceedings, 1971-1972 1978-1987 (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Meeting Materials
        - Meetings, 1955-1984 (Box-folder 2/4)
        - Meetings, 1968 (Box-folder 2/5)
        - Meetings, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 2/6)
        - Meetings, 1999 (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Meetings, 2000 (Box-folder 2/8)
        - Meetings, 2001 (Box-folder 2/9)
        - Meetings, 2002 (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Meetings, 2003-2005 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Membership Information
      - Membership Lists, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Membership Lists, 2002 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Membership Profiles, 2005 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Financial Records, 1966-2005; Subseries 2
    - Transactions Paid, Received, Expense Reports, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Statements; Invoices, Transactions Paid and Received, 1974-1977 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Treasurer/Auditor Reports; Statements, 1966-1976 1977 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Transactions Paid and Received, 1978 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Statements, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Check and Deposit Register, 1978-1984 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Invoices, Receipts, and Deposit Slips, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Statements, Invoices, and Transactions, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Reports, Invoices and Transactions, 1995-2005 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Transportation Partnership Funding Package, 2005 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Correspondence, 1913-2005; Subseries 3
    - General, 1913-1962 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - General, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - General, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - General, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - General, 2003-2005 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Received and Sent, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Received and Sent, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Sam Hill Bridge Dedication, 1964 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Activities, 1998-2003; 1920-2003; Subseries 4
    - Newsletters, 1998-2002 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Centennial Celebration, 1999 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Lobby Information, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Pamphlets, 2000 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Resolutions, undated (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Legislative Breakfast, 2003 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - General, 1920-1930 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Clippings, 1917-2000; Subseries 5
    - Clippings, 1917-2000 (Box-folder 5/11)
    - 41st Session Washington State Legislature, 1969 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Photos, undated; Subseries 6
    - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
- North End Improvement Council (NEIC) & Other Organizations, 1926-1980; Series II
  - North End Improvement Council (NEIC), 1926-1960; Subseries 1
    - Administrative Records, 1926-1958
      - Journal of By-laws, Meetings, Finances, 1926-1942 (Box-folder 6/1)
      - By-laws, 1928-1956 (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1943-1955 (Box-folder 6/3)
      - Meeting Proceedings, Reports, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 6/4)
      - Advisory Board Meeting Proceedings, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Financial Records, 1955-1960
      - Bank Statements and Ledgers, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 6/6)
      - Kitsap County Road District #1 Quarter Reports, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1959
      - General, 1951-1956 (Box-folder 6/8)
      - General, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Kitsap County Good Roads Association, 1954-1960; Subseries 2
    - Correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - North Olympic Chamber of Commerce, 1956-1957; Subseries 3
    - Subject File, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Other Good Roads Associations, 1979-1980; Subseries 4
    - Pamphlets and Statements, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 6/12)